Well, welcome back to the tool call.
This room today and tomorrow is all about practical stuff.
This is where I want to be.
It's no like Sea Level.
Heady takes about what AI is and isn't.
It's like, what can we actually use today and tomorrow?
So my Walter is here.
She is the co-founder of hood, and she's going to be talking
about the difference, the chasm, if you will, between
what agents think they do well and what they actually do well.
So can we give her a round of applause, please?
All right.
So welcome everyone.
Thank you for for taking the time and and joining after lunch.
Hopefully it will.
I have added some points in which, you know, you might wake up
a little bit and might might be funny.
We'll see.
So I wanted to start with the situation that kind of led us to
this actual use case, which is a situation you might know.
There's this PM saying, oh my God, this page is so slow.
We have to do something about them, about it.
And then they text the engineering managers like, so can we optimize it?
And then Ben would say probably, but I'd have to dig in to find out.
And then they say, oh, never mind then, right.
Because they're busy, they're doing things right.
And then a few weeks later she would say, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
But this is actually too slow.
Now we're going to have to do something about it.
How long will it take what he says?
Well, I don't know. Right.
Somewhere between an hour and a week, I.
I'll have to look, Okay. And.
And who can even take this?
The answer is only Dave.
He is the only one that has any idea what's going on in that code base.
The rest are not in the company for like five years. So.
So just Dave and our one of our customers
started with this situation where they were constantly in this.
We have to fix this.
We have no idea how, but we can't prioritize it phase.
And then we said, well, maybe we can do something about it.
So mine co-founder and CEO
had we're building a runtime intelligence layer for coding agent.
So it's basically a sensor that runs with your app in production
and captures what coding agents need to reason overproduction.
So like for every function, how often it runs, how long it takes,
whether it's failing and when something goes wrong, it
proactively captures deep forensic context about why that happened.
So that when you ask why is this slow or why is this failing,
you can actually get an answer. And.
The big problem is that, you know,
it got easier to build and to generate code.
And then you kind of have this like, yeah, it looks good to me.
And a bunch of pull requests.
That looks good.
You have one agent that build them.
You have another agent that says, yeah, that looks great.
This is a great idea.
And then the question that you ask yourself is,
why is this broken like
but but but why it like all the tests were passing and everything was fine
and and code still finds creative ways to fail in production.
And we still do that, like with the best tools
and the best engineers and the best days of the universe.
And the coding agents have no idea how that actually behaves.
And we are basically obsessing about how come
this can live alongside this at scale.
So maybe
there's an agent we can build for that.
And basically I'm going to go over the journey that we had from there.
Why was that even important for them, how they did it from a how
we did it from a tech perspective and most importantly,
how we thought we would do it and it didn't work.
And what we did about that, and also how it worked from a process
perspective, which I think is also very important today to understand
how to connect all these dots from it kind of works from a technical
perspective to people are actually using it and summarize
what we can take out of this so that leaks faster than we bail.
And I think that was true for humans as well.
We kind of ignore the issue and then it degrades and then it becomes a crisis.
And now we have to prioritize it.
So we we fix it.
I don't know.
Does anyone relate or is it just us?
Okay, okay. We're good.
We're good. So you're okay.
It just so happens that everyone is doing this,
and it's not because we're stupid, and it's not because we don't care.
It's because we're very busy building features, which is what we are here to do.
We're ingenious.
We're builders.
So we try to ignore things because they might not be as important.
And then once they get to that crisis mode,
we want to fix them as soon as possible so that we can go back to building.
That is a leaky bucket by definition.
So the research phase is a big problem there, because if I knew
that I can fix it in a day, I would probably prioritize that.
But what I have to do is to pay just to find out.
It's kind of like taking something from the grocery store and then going
all the way to the cashier just to know how much it costs
so that you understand if you want it or not.
And that's what we've been doing for years.
We were like, okay, let's invest a few hours
and then we can understand what can be done.
And magically there's always something we can do, right?
But we weren't aware of it.
And then when we know that something could take an hour to three weeks,
we don't want to prioritize it because we don't know
what we're going to get out of it.
We don't know how much optimization we're going to get.
So you don't know how much it costs.
You don't know what impact it has, and you're expected to just prioritize
that in your day to day life, comparing to features
that give value to the customer.
So that doesn't really add up.
So our thought was to automate the investigation part.
It wasn't even about fixing it.
It was just about knowing what can be done automatically
and then being able to streamline the fix.
So what if we just run on a weekly basis or biweekly,
depending on your sprint planning sequences, and just know
about real sweet spot with high ROI opportunities
that are scored so we can just run it every week, and that performance sprint
that we've been trying to get to for months can just happen regularly.
Sounds pretty good, except that it was pretty hard.
So let's talk about what we did there and what was helpful.
All right.
Did I convince you about why this is needed?
Great. That's good.
That's a good start.
I think a lot of times when you're talking about agenda
workflows, the first question is like, does it really need to be built?
And it gets so much easier to build stuff that we just stumble on building things
because they're fun and, you know, auto triage and all these things are like
very good examples of that.
I think what was interesting about this case is that we were trying to automate
something that is not a part of our day to day lives.
In the same way.
This is built for how agents work, which is kind of like this automatic thing.
You won't stop every week and ask an engineer
to kind of go over and find some interesting performance optimizations.
But if you knew that they exist
and that engineer would just like slack, their team lead saying, hey,
I just found this thing, like in two hours we can get this down 30%.
They would say, wow, that's amazing, right?
So maybe that's sort of the first wedge to change that behavior.
So let's talk about how that works.
First of
all, we needed to ask the question of where can this run.
Because agentic workflows don't.
We don't want them to run on our computers.
We want something to run in the cloud.
And it just so happens that not every customer
we work with even has their own setup for that.
And we have players like cursor and others
that are building their automations so that it's very, very easy to install.
But at the same time, you're
now locked to that specific vendor, which does not make sense at scale.
So we wanted something that's vendor neutral,
both in terms of the compute as in where it runs in terms of the harness,
as in which coding agent is and which model we choose.
We don't know.
No one knows what's the best.
There are seasons.
And then what we wanted to do is to make it easy to switch.
We wanted it to be secure.
Of course, in terms of the permissions the tool calls, the authentication,
we don't want to build something for scratch.
We want to use something that we can trust.
We want a set of triggers
that could be webhooks like, hey, this is slow, let's investigate it.
And also on schedules that are per deployment
or on a weekly basis or whatever that they different teams would want.
And we wanted it to be easy to maintain and update, which is what I think
people get most most wrong about agentic workflows
is you don't just ship them, they are like code.
You ship them and then you find out something and you just want to change
and tweak that little thing so that it will be easier to work with.
And then if it's hard to do that, then people just won't.
And in our case, the biggest question was what matters?
And that's something that is live and changes with your business and products.
So it was very important for us.
Specifically, we chose GitHub Agentic Workflows.
I don't know if you're familiar with that, but there's actually a guy that built it
in the audience. You can talk to him later.
And the idea was that
people already have GitHub Actions or those similar.
Not everyone, but many of them.
So we can just start with something that they already know,
that they already trust, that has these parameters in place.
Again, it's not the only solution, but it was something feasible.
We don't want to innovate.
We don't want to build this new agent
infrastructure for whatever and prioritizes with the platform team.
We have GitHub actions.
So now we can have those in a way that works.
And again it's about reducing friction and finding that path
of least resistance to just trying something out and see if it works.
So that's kind of how it looks like.
And if we go over it a bit more thoroughly,
is it big enough we can do this.
The first thing is you actually choose the engine, as in
where do you want to run it?
And is it cloud or codex or whatever, which permissions you have, the network,
the tools and so on.
The MCP servers — in this case, Hud's MCP server.
And then you just start talking. So
the task is basically a prompt
that runs every once in a while or triggered and does that.
And if I go back to here, you can see that
it's basically a weekly report of an AI performance and reliability
engineer for the repo that generates this deep insights
and context about the repo and what it does.
And this was actually we started with the repository.
And then we even like
did it more ingrained because a lot of people are still using monolith.
And the idea is not this report
about all the cool things that we can theoretically do.
It's about the thing that the tech lead for that specific service cares about.
So they are getting designated report only on the parts that they care about.
So basically we have a coding agent could be cloud or anything else.
Specifically we use Claude.
And the runtime intelligence runs weekly
on GitHub actions and sends the report to slack.
And again this I'm not saying this is the only way to make it work.
What I'm actually saying is find a way that matches your stack
and your tools so that it would be as easy as possible.
They were using Claude Code, GitHub and slack.
So that's why it made a lot of sense for us to kind of latch onto that.
But let's talk about what it does.
Right.
What we basically want is to start with the production context,
have the agent analyze it to find anti-pattern and opportunities.
Then we want to score and flag them, because not everything that can be done
should be done.
And that's because we still have to review that code and merge it to production.
It's because we want to make sure that it actually has an impact, and we
don't want to take a risk on a deployment if it's not going to be that impactful.
And again, I hope no one relates to that.
But a lot of times what happens in performance
is you start with a thesis and then you fix it, then you deploy,
and it's not exactly as impactful as you expected it to be.
It was really great in staging, but in production
the problem isn't really that.
So we tried to avoid that and to sort of convince something that's worth doing
and then go over the diff and merge the PR
with a human review, and that sort of closes the loop.
And then it
didn't work right, because that's how it is.
First of all, some of these offers were plausible
but unverified, which is kind of like what we do when we go over the code.
It's like, well, we can probably optimize this,
but we don't know if that's really the bottleneck.
If something is taking 20s or five
seconds, I'm not sure exactly where that time is spent.
So things that sound right are not necessarily
the ones that are going to move the needle.
Second was specifically for queries.
So queries can be very complex.
And also they are very dependent on how the code actually runs
and where the data is.
If you have that customer with like 10,000 rows returning
from the database, it's not a big surprise that it's going to take longer.
It's just that you have no idea how that looks like.
And of course, the biggest, biggest problem is what we call the lazy fix,
which means, oh, there's an exception, let's catch it.
This is great, but it's not helpful at all.
And a lot of time, what happens is that if you try to optimize
for the syntax error or the long running query,
then the question and the answer will be local.
And we actually want to look at it from a broader perspective.
So those are like things that I guess it's fine that they will start that way.
But in time, we understood that.
We want to explain what a fix does look like
and what what am I interested in, kind of like a staff engineer
would explain to someone who just joined the team.
And all you need is context, right?
And there are only two problems with context.
One is you might have too much of it, and then it's really hard to understand
what matters.
And the other is you might not have enough and then it won't matter
because the agent would just assume what's going on there.
Or what I would do as an engineer is I would probably add more logs or metrics,
deploy a version, gather context, understand
where the bottleneck is, and then go and fix it.
What the agent will do is to say, okay, this is what I have.
Let's find the shortest path.
Let's let's assume, take some assumptions and see where that goes.
We can't do that to scale, especially if we want to interrupt engineers flow.
Right. That's like the most important.
We love that.
So if I am going to flag an opportunity, I can't risk
just saying something that won't really make sense
because then they will read my report, they will open a pull request,
they will review it and then deploy it
and then find out that it didn't change anything.
And then I just wasted their time.
So it was really important for us to make sure
that we have just enough context so that we can understand
and have confidence in the fact that it's actually going to do something.
But that's actually hard to do because they don't speak the same language.
You know, the production context is usually in service level
or endpoint level.
This endpoint takes five seconds and the P99 is six
six seconds, and the P 100 is 17 seconds.
And then the agent the agent reasons overcoat right.
The local functions and the files and the class methods.
It can kind of deduct the connection between the two,
but they don't speak the same language.
And that's where most of the of the problem is when you ask
why is it long.
It could go over the code and it might get it right.
Don't get me wrong, some of the issues can be found in static
analysis, but when we want to make that transition between
human lead to an agent workflow, we have to be quite certain
in our confidence so that we can truly automate it.
If something works 90% of the time.
It's not an automation, it's streamlining humans.
And that's
why we built what we call prod to code, which is basically a mapping
of what's going on in production to the function level.
So you have like the endpoint or the service
and the endpoints or event consumers and the job cron jobs that it runs,
and then the mapping of the functions that are involved within it.
So one thing that we got from this is the ability to ask this is slow why.
But it also opened a huge window
of opportunity to ask the inverse question of I'm going to touch this.
What does that impact?
And should I care about it?
Is it going to touch my payments and my authorization or not?
So basically
what the sensor is doing in
that aspect is complete function level context in a way
that's connected to the endpoint and deep forensic context only when it needed.
And the assumption here is that we can't just go through like
gigabytes of logs and spans and traces to be able to do that.
But if we have for each of these functions, the ability to connect them to
how often it runs, which business flows, does it impact, how long it takes,
and whether it's failing, then we can start going over
the deeper context, whether that's logs or traces or whatever,
when we kind of have the area of where we are trying to to tap into,
and that's the same level at which the coding agents reason.
So we have the
basic query language layer we specifically use ClickHouse for that.
But of course every team has their own.
And on top of that we can build a set of skills
because it's not just enough to connect the skills
to connect the data and kind of ask the agent to see what happens there.
I saw like five different talks about why that fails.
So we have the skills of how to approach an HTTP 500,
how to approach a memory leak, how to approach a performance degradation.
And all of a sudden it's not just Dave that can tap into that knowledge
and expand it.
And on top of that, or the level of the automations.
So auto fix or dead code removal, a building on top of those skills
that are building on top of the query language.
And I think it was really important in terms of what we learned to allow
all of these layers.
The coding agent might need something
that I cannot express in words, and that's why tools are not enough.
But at the same time, I don't want to waste my tokens
and my chain of thought on things that I know.
I do know how to tackle a memory leak.
I want to look at the pod that's had that memory leak.
I want to look at a different one that didn't,
and I want to see what happened there.
That didn't happen there. Right?
I when I look at the performance degradation,
I want to understand where the time is being spent.
So that small level of involvement
and ownership on the methodology was very impactful for us.
And then we can say something like, look for artificial
delays like sleeps and timeouts,
look for n plus one queries, look for missing indexes or synchronous
blocking or sequential awaits all of these things.
And when you think of a code base that exists in their case
for 15 years, obviously these things are there.
It's just that we need to kind of dig them out and know that they exist.
And then you have these moments
we're like, oh my God, this was like this for six years.
Are you serious?
But if we look at it from a positive perspective, there's like
so much we can do.
And I think in that aspect that gave us that
balance between
kind of letting it run free and having that full,
full freedom, but also kind of guiding it to how we know
that engineering practices and skills work.
And then we can ask something like, why are my endpoints taking so long,
like my product manager asks, and get an answer of, oh, there's actually this thing
with an N plus one query that exists in the code base for like six years.
Maybe we can do something about this.
And we were very happy and pleased about the results.
So we said, okay, maybe
we can just like add open pull requests for all of these high impact, low
risk changes that don't require migrations or anything super scary.
And we can just open a pull request.
No no no no no,
we don't want any pull requests that no one's going to go over
and we don't want to go over those 80 progress even though they exist.
And I think that's like if I if you can take one thing out of
this is like after you get it working and you want to automate it,
think about the scale and think about the humans that are still in the loop.
We're not in the point where no one just cares about it.
And if you open a pull requests, it's kind of like opening your Datadog
and Sentry with those like 700 issues that all they say is like, well,
I'm not going to be able to fix this, so I'm not even going to try.
So we of course, we started with automated pull requests.
We realized no one cares about that.
And if it's not prioritized, then they're not going to do something about it.
And again, I am not complaining.
I'm not judging.
We're builders, right?
We have prioritization and it exists for a reason.
No one has time to just go over a bunch of four requests built by the agent
that are statistically huge, and try to understand what happens.
We don't want to own that.
We don't want to go into it.
So we actually need to convince the human that it's worth the attention.
Instead of convincing the agent
that it's worth the tokens, he will always think that they are.
So we map the hot paths that endpoints
that are invoked often the business impact of that.
So is this impacting payments or authentication
or the set of things that you already know that you care about for your business?
And also the risk?
We are not looking for the best optimizations.
We are looking for the highest impact, lowest risk changes that can be done
so that we can go to the developer or the PM and say, hey, listen,
it's like that small and it's going to do like 30% improvement.
So we should do that and we want to make that humanly readable.
So if a human gets something like hey, this endpoint is like
the P90 is around 100 milliseconds, except it kind of takes 45 seconds
every once in a while, and we have no idea why, theoretically speaking.
And then it would be, oh, this is happening
because you always use the Mongols distinct function.
If you switch it to a search, then that should slow you down
like improve like 30, 40%.
And this is something that we can actually prioritize.
And once we started talking about these quick wins,
you can see that they can either open it to to dive deeper,
they can create a ticket or create a PR because again,
I don't want to be opinionated on exactly how advanced they are.
That's fine.
Either of those work, we can do it later.
We can do it now.
Obviously, both are labeled so that we can measure it.
And all of a sudden that endpoint that used to take 100 milliseconds,
except the fact that it kind of takes 45 seconds every once in a while.
Well, it doesn't anymore.
And I think that was a very,
very big learning for us that we just want to get to a point where
the humans kind of make the decision that it's worth a while.
The fact that merging to production did not become it's
not free, it's just cheaper to to merge and to ship.
And then we kind of have the ability to learn more about it.
So for things you can take from our experience
so far, one, we still need to define what matters.
And I think if I can be a bit philosophical, even though
it's a use case, I think that's going to be a huge part
of what we do as engineers in the future is decide what's worth a while,
worth the tokens,
worth the time, whether it's a human that's reviewing it or an agent.
We still define what matters more and what matters less than the ability
to score by what will be impactful for the business is really important.
And I think that's that's something that we can all take to our day to day lives.
And if we inform our agents on how we look at what they do,
then they're going to do better because they don't just lack the runtime context.
They also lack the business context.
Second part is to automate the investigation phase to
make prioritization better.
And this is an example that we had for performance.
We're doing similar things for reliability and the other things.
But I'm not saying that the backlog should be empty
just because we have agents.
I'm saying that we have a way
to use the agents to make better decisions on what to prioritize.
And this is a use case that is not as common as what we're seeing.
Like a lot of people are using agents to do what they were planned to do faster,
and this was a way for us to help people
prioritize the the ROI and not just the task itself.
Context over cleverness, I guess.
Like it's it's it seems obvious, but the agents get useful
once they see what's going on.
In our case, it was production context, being able to understand where it is
and to have very high signal data about it
so that they can build it the same way that a staff engineer
cannot just move to a different company and ship to production on day one.
That's the context that matters,
and it's going to change their behavior the same way that it changes our behavior.
And last but not least, Agentic engineering
is not like coding with an agent.
It is different.
If we want something to work as a workflow, it has to actually work
and it has to be confident in what it does.
It is better to do less but the right things.
And if I at any time I would suggest something that won't work.
We lose trust in the process, so the automation unlocks
continuous impact, but it also requires a higher confidence level.
So choose the things that you feel
that your repo and your automation level are ripe for.
But I think that's where we're going.
And when we try to think about that, our core engineers,
when we know the scale, we can architect the system.
So I think the scale that we're going to see,
and the question that I'm asking myself is, how would would it look like
to get to a point where some engineers and some of our customers
companies would actually just click that merge button and get that fixed as is?
And because I can measure it now,
we can get better and better until we get to that point.
And I think, you know,
we can talk a lot about how that would be perfect if it just works.
But the thing that was, I think really int about the process
here is the ability to start with something that is still net positive,
and it allows you that flywheel of understanding where it got stuck,
where the insights not good enough. Were they good enough.
But it was hard to merge them.
Did we merge them.
But they they didn't give that effect that we tried.
And that let's us learn and improve.
Before we get to that point of full automation.
And again, my dream is to get to a point where people would say, well,
80% of the time we just did the exact same thing
and we kind of merged it to main, and then we will know that
we're ready, but we're providing value along the way as we're getting there.
When the models are getting better, the context is getting better,
and everyone can kind of spend their time on on the right things.
So thank you.
I hope that was somewhat helpful.
I appreciate your attention
in this tough hour and we have some time for questions.
Right. We have one minute, one questions.
If someone has a very quick question
anyone?
One in the back.
Yeah.
If someone has a question that requires more than a minute,
I'll stay outside to to answer them.
Thanks a lot for the talk.
I have one question.
So most people we probably already have integrated with, like Datadog
or Sentry or some other, like platform where you need
to ingest loads of data to be able to get all these production metrics.
So how do you stay competitive with it?
Because, yeah, I guess you need to
also ingest that amount of data, but then people won't be like, oh, well,
we just like also pay you 10-K a month or whatever to be able to do this stuff.
So to how do you figure that out?
That's a huge question and especially for a startup.
So we always like to say that we're like an espresso shop.
We only have a spesso, but it's the best one in town.
We try to focus on the thing that we do better.
If they have Datadog or all these tools, we will ask, okay, but
do you still suffer from production incidents and issues?
Do you still spend way too much time?
Are you still surprised by issues that your customers report?
And if so, let's run together, obviously, like for example, distributed tracing.
If they have that, we will just connect to what they already have.
The thing is the function level context and the forensic context
that is being proactively captured.
And we focus on that and integrate to whatever it is that they have.
Okay.
Thank you so much. My.